<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Convict</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Lyrical Ballads</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Poems transcribed from OCR and Page Scans of the 1798 Edition of Lyrical Ballads held at Simon Fraser University</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <pb facs="Wordsworth_1798_215.png" n="197"/>
      <head rend="centre uppercase font-size(3mm)">THE CONVICT.</head>
      <figure type="double-line" rend="length(15mm)"/>
      <lg type="poem">
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>The glory of the evening was spread through the west;</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">—On the slope of a mountain I stood,</l>
          <l>While the joy that precedes the calm season of rest </l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">Rang loud through the meadow and wood.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>“ And must we then part from a dwelling so fair?"</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">In the pain of my spirit I said, </l>
          <l>And with a deep sadness I turned, to repair </l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">To the cell where the convict is laid.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>The thick-ribbed walls that o’ershadow the gate</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">Resound; and the dungeons unfold:</l>
          <l>I pause; and at length, through the glimmering grate,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">That outcast of pity behold.</l>
        </lg>
        <pb facs="Wordsworth_1798_216.png" n="198"/>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>His black matted head on his shoulder is bent,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">And deep is the sigh of his breath,</l>
          <l>And with stedfast dejection his eyes are intent</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">On the fetters that link him to death.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>'Tis sorrow enough on that visage to gaze,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">That body dismiss’d from his care ;</l>
          <l>Yet my fancy has pierced to his heart, and pourtrays </l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">More terrible images there.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>His bones are consumed, and his life-blood is dried,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">With wishes the past to undo ;</l>
          <l>And his crime, through the pains that o’erwhelm him,</l>
          <l rend="indent(7.5mm)">descried,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">Still blackens and grows on his view.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>When from the dark synod, or blood-reeking field,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">To his chamber the monarch is led,</l>
          <l>All soothers of sense their soft virtue shall yield,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">And quietness pillow his head.</l>
        </lg>
        <pb facs="Wordsworth_1798_217.png" n="199"/>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>But if grief, self-consumed, in oblivion would doze,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">And conscience her tortures appease,</l>
          <l>’Mid tumult and uproar this man must repose ;</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">In the comfortless vault of disease.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>When his fetters at night have so press’d on his limbs,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">That the weight can no longer be borne,</l>
          <l>If, while a half-slumber his memory bedims,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">The wretch on his pallet should turn,</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>While the jail-mastiff howls at the dull clanking chain,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">From the roots of his hair there shall start</l>
          <l>A thousand sharp punctures of cold-sweating pain,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">And terror shall leap at his heart.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>But now he half-raises his deep-sunken eye,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">And the motion unsettles a tear;</l>
          <l>The silence of sorrow it seems to supply,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">And asks of me why I am here.</l>
        </lg>
        <pb facs="Wordsworth_1798_218.png" n="200"/>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>“ Poor victim ! no idle intruder has stood</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">"  With o’erweening complacence our state to compare,</l>
          <l>"  But one, whose first wish is the wish to be good,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">"  Is come as a brother thy sorrows to share.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>“ At thy name though compassion her nature resign,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">“  Though in virtue’s proud mouth thy report be a </l>
          <l rend="indent(7.5mm)">stain,</l>
          <l>My care, if the arm of the mighty were mine,</l>
          <l rend="indent(5mm)">“  Would plant thee where yet thou might’st blossom </l>
          <l rend="indent(7.5mm)">again.”</l>
        </lg>
      </lg>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
