<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" ?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Foster Mother's Tale, A Dramatic Fragment</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Lyrical Ballads</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>
                    Poems transcribed from OCR and Page Scans of the 1798 Edition of Lyrical Ballads held at Simon Fraser University
                </p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <pb facs="Wordsworth_1798_069.png"/>
            <head rend="centre uppercase font-size(2mm)">
                <title type="sub" rend="centre uppercase italics font-size(3mm)">THE FOSTER-MOTHER'S TALE,</title>
                <title type="sub" rend="centre uppercase font-size(2mm)">A DRAMATIC FRAGMENT.</title>
            </head>
            <figure type="double-line" rend="length(15mm)"/>
            <sp>
                <speaker rend="centre uppercase">FOSTER-MOTHER.</speaker>
                <lg>
                    <l>I never saw the man whom you describe.</l>
                </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker rend="centre uppercase">MARIA.</speaker>
                <lg>
                    <l>’Tis strange ! he spake of you familiarly</l>
                    <l>As mine and Albert's common Foster-mother.</l>
                </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker rend="centre uppercase">FOSTER-MOTHER.</speaker>
                <lg>
                    <l>Now blessings on the man, whoe’er he be,</l>
                    <l>
                        That joined your names with mine ! O my sweet lady,
                    </l>
                    <l>As often as I think of those dear times</l>
                    <l>When you two little ones would stand at eve</l>
                    <l>On each side of my chair, and make me learn</l>
                    <l>All you had learnt in the day ; and how to talk</l>
                    <pb facs="Wordsworth_1798_070.png" n="54"/>
                    <l>In gentle phrase, then bid me sing to you—</l>
                    <l>
                        'Tis more like heaven to come than what
                        <hi rend="italics">has</hi>
                        been.
                    </l>
                </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker rend="centre uppercase">MARIA.</speaker>
                <lg>
                    <l>O my dear Mother ! this strange man has left me</l>
                    <l>Troubled with wilder fancies, than the moon</l>
                    <l>Breeds in the love-sick maid who gazes at it,</l>
                    <l>Till lost in inward vision, with wet eye</l>
                    <l>She gazes idly !—But that entrance, Mother!</l>
                </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker rend="centre uppercase">FOSTER-MOTHER.</speaker>
                <lg><l>Can no one hear ? It is a perilous tale !</l></lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker rend="centre uppercase">MARIA.</speaker>
                <lg><l>No one.</l></lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker rend="centre uppercase">FOSTER-MOTHER.</speaker>
                <lg>
                    <l rend="indent(5mm)">My husband’s father told it me,</l>
                    <l>Poor old Leoni !—Angels rest his soul !</l>
                    <l>He was a woodman, and could fell and saw</l>
                    <l>With lusty arm. You know that huge round beam</l>
                    <l>Which props the hanging wall of the old chapel ?</l>
                    <l>Beneath that tree, while yet it was a tree</l>
                    <pb facs="Wordsworth_1798_071.png" n="55"/>
                    <l>He found a baby wrapt in mosses, lined</l>
                    <l>With thistle-beards, and such small locks of wool</l>
                    <l>As hang on brambles. Well, he brought him home,</l>
                    <l>And reared him at the then Lord Velez’ cost.</l>
                    <l>And so the babe grew up a pretty boy,</l>
                    <l>A pretty boy, but most unteachable—</l>
                    <l>And never learnt a prayer, nor told a bead,</l>
                    <l>
                        But knew the names of birds, and mocked their notes,
                    </l>
                    <l>And whistled, as he were a bird himself:</l>
                    <l>And all the autumn ’twas his only play</l>
                    <l>
                        To get the seeds of wild flowers, and to plant them
                    </l>
                    <l>With earth and water, on the stumps of trees.</l>
                    <l>A Friar, who gathered simples in the wood,</l>
                    <l>A grey-haired man—he loved this little boy,</l>
                    <l>The boy loved him—and, when the Friar taught him,</l>
                    <l>
                        He soon could write with the pen : and from that time,
                    </l>
                    <l>Lived chiefly at the Convent or the Castle.</l>
                    <l>So he became a very learned youth.</l>
                    <l>
                        But Oh ! poor wretch !—he read, and read, and read,
                    </l>
                    <l>’Till his brain turned—and ere his twentieth year,</l>
                    <pb facs="Wordsworth_1798_072.png" n="56"/>
                    <l>He had unlawful thoughts of many things :</l>
                    <l>And though he prayed, he never loved to pray</l>
                    <l>With holy men, nor in a holy place—</l>
                    <l>But yet his speech, it was so soft and sweet,</l>
                    <l>The late Lord Velez ne’er was wearied with him.</l>
                    <l>And once, as by the north side of the Chapel</l>
                    <l>They stood together, chained in deep discourse,</l>
                    <l>The earth heaved under them with such a groan,</l>
                    <l>That the wall tottered, and had well-nigh fallen</l>
                    <l>
                        Right on their heads. My Lord was sorely frightened;
                    </l>
                    <l>A fever seized him, and he made confession</l>
                    <l>Of all the heretical and lawless talk</l>
                    <l>
                        Which brought this judgment : so the youth was seized
                    </l>
                    <l>And cast into that hole. My husband’s father</l>
                    <l>Sobbed like a child—it almost broke his heart:</l>
                    <l>And once as he was working in the cellar,</l>
                    <l>He heard a voice distinctly ; ’twas the youth’s,</l>
                    <l>Who sung a doleful song about green fields,</l>
                    <l>How sweet it were on lake or wild savannah,</l>
                    <l>To hunt for food, and be a naked man,</l>
                    <pb facs="Wordsworth_1798_073.png" n="57"/>
                    <l>And wander up and down at liberty.</l>
                    <l>He always doted on the youth, and now</l>
                    <l>His love grew desperate ; and defying death,</l>
                    <l>He made that cunning entrance I described :</l>
                    <l>And the young man escaped.</l>
                </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker rend="centre uppercase">MARIA.</speaker>
                <lg>
                    <l rend="indent(10mm)">'Tis a sweet tale :</l>
                    <l>Such as would lull a listening child to sleep,</l>
                    <l>His rosy face besoiled with unwiped tears.—</l>
                    <l>And what became of him ?</l>
                </lg>
            </sp>
            <sp>
                <speaker rend="centre uppercase">FOSTER-MOTHER.</speaker>
                <lg>
                    <l rend="indent(10mm)">He went on ship-board</l>
                    <l>With those bold voyagers, who made discovery</l>
                    <l>Of golden lands. Leoni’s younger brother</l>
                    <l>
                        Went likewise, and when he returned to
                        <rs type="place">Spain</rs>
                        ,
                    </l>
                    <l>He told Leoni, that the poor mad youth,</l>
                    <l>Soon after they arrived in that new world,</l>
                    <l>In spite of his dissuasion, seized a boat,</l>
                    <l>And all alone, set sail by silent moonlight</l>
                    <pb facs="Wordsworth_1798_074.png" n="58"/>
                    <l>Up a great river, great as any sea,</l>
                    <l>And ne’er was heard of more : but ’tis supposed,</l>
                    <l>He lived and died among the savage men.</l>
                </lg>
            </sp>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
